本节我们看确定性加密的概念
In this segment, we're gonna look at the
concept of deterministic encryption that
这在实际中经常出现。当我说确定性加密系统时
often comes up in practice. When I say
deterministic encryption system, I mean an
我是指一个加密系统总是把给定明文映射到同一个密文
encryption system that will always map
given message to exactly the same cipher
如果我们加密同样的明文三次
text. So if we encrypt the same message
three times, every time we'll get exactly
每次我们都会得到同样的密文。这里没有用到新鲜值
the same cipher text. So there are no
nonces involved here. Literally this is
这只是一个一致性加密机制，对特定的明文
just a consistence encryption scheme that
will always output the same cipher text
总是输出同样的密文。那么我们将在实际中看到它
given a particular message. So let's see
where this comes up in practice and in
特别地，我想给大家看查找加密的数据库的例子
particular, I want to show you the case of
look-ups into an encrypted database. So
设定是这样的：我们这里有一个服务器，存储了
the settings are imagine we have a server
here that is going to store information
一个加密的数据库。它存储的是记录
inside of an encrypted database. So what
it will store is records, and every record
每条记录都有一个索引，一些数据存储在记录里
has an index and some data that's stored
inside of the record. Now, the first thing
现在，服务器首先要加密这条记录
the server's gonna do is, it's gonna
encrypt this record. So here's a record
这是一个加密了的记录，大家注意这个索引
被加密了，使用了密钥K1
became encrypted and you notice that the
index became encrypted with K1 and the
数据也被加密了，用的密钥K2，然后
加密好的记录被发送给了数据库
data is encrypted with K2 and then the
encrypted record is sent over to the
同样的事情发生在许多记录上，这样整个数据库
database. And the same thing happens to
many records so that the database overall
保存了许多加密的记录。大家可以想象
holds many, many encrypted records. Well,
again, you can imagine that the index is
索引使用密钥K1加密，数据和记录使用密钥K2加密
encrypted using the key K1 and then the
data and the records is encrypted using
现在，如果加密是确定性的，有件好事是
the key K2. Now, if encryption is
deterministic, the nice thing about that
稍后，当服务器想提取数据库中的一条记录时
is that, at a later time, when the server
wants to retrieve a record from the
他只需要向数据库发送加密后的
database, all he needs to do is send to
the database an encryption of the index
服务器感兴趣的记录的索引。这里它会发送
加密后的索引"Alice"
that the server is interested in. So here,
it would send an encryption of the index,
这也是加密的，获得的密文
Alice. That again, becomes encrypted, and
the resulting cipher text is identical to
与最初写入数据库时生成的密文一样
the cipher text that was generated when
the record was first written to the
然后数据库可以找到这个记录，里面有
database. And the database can then, you
know, find the record that has this
这个加密的索引，然后把结果发送给服务器
encrypted index in it, and then send the
result back to the server. The nice thing
这里的好事是，数据库完全蒙在鼓里
about this is that now the database is
completely in the dark as to what data is
完全不知道数据库里存了什么数据，它甚至不知道
服务器提取了什么记录
stored in the database and it doesn't even
know what records are being retrieved by
因为数据库看到的请求都是密文形式的
the server since all it sees are basically
requests for encrypted entices. And so
这就是确定的加密机制。我们做一个数据库里的
this deterministic encryption mechanism.
Let's just do a quick look up in the
简单查询，给定一个加密的索引，
我们保证，由于确定性加密的性质
database given an encrypted index and
we're guaranteed that because of the
这个索引将会以与记录被创建时
deterministic encryption property that the
index is going to be encrypted in exactly
严格相同的方式被加密。这可能对很多人来说会有麻烦
the same way as if was when the record was
created. And so this should be disturbing
因为我们之前说过，确定性加密
to many of you because we previously said
that deterministic encryption simply
不可能是选择明文安全的。问题是，
攻击者可以看不同的密文
cannot be chosen plain text secure. The
problem is that an attacker can look at
如果他看到同样的密文两次
different cipher text and if he sees the
same cipher text twice he knows that the
他就知道底层被加密的明文一定是一样的。
换句话说，通过看密文
underlying encrypted messages must also be
the same. So in other words, by looking at
攻击者可以学到一些对应明文的信息
cipher text, he can learn something about
the corresponding plain text because every
因为每次他看到同样的密文两次时，他就知道
底层的明文是相等的
time he sees the same cipher text twice,
he knows that the underlying messages are
实际中，这会带来严重的攻击
equal. In practice, this leads to
significant attacks, and particularly when
特别地，当明文空间很小时，例如，
如果我们在网络中传递单个字节
the message space is small. For example,
if we're transmitting single bytes across
比如一次传递一个键盘的敲击结果
the network, such as, keystrokes that are
being transmitted one keystroke at a time.
(可以参考Telnet协议里的情形)
事实上，攻击者可以为所有可能的密文
Then, in fact, an attacker can simply
build a dictionary of all possible cipher
构建一个字典。如果只有单个字节，那么
总共只有256种可能的密文
texts. If it's only single bytes, then
there will only be 256 possible cipher
然后，通过学习这些密文的解密结果
texts. And then, simply by learning what
the decryptions of those cipher texts are,
攻击者可以解出所有的未来密文，通过简单地查找
he can actually figure out all future
cipher texts, simply by looking them up,
在这个字典里。有很多情况的明文很小
in this dictionary. And so there are many
cases where the message being so small,
这时确定性加密是不安全的。具体而言
where this, deterministic encryption,
simply is insecure. Now concretely, in the
在加密数据库的情况下，攻击者会看到
case of an encrypted database, what the
attacker would see is if there are two
如果有两个记录在索引位置正好有同样的密文
records that happen to have the same
cipher text in the index position then now
那么他就知道了这两条记录对应同一个索引
he knows that those two records correspond
to the same index. So again, even though
尽管他不知道索引是什么，他也能学习到
he doesn't know what the index is, he
learns something about the corresponding
明文的信息。我想简单地提醒大家，形式化地
plain text. I wanted to briefly remind you
that, formally, we say that deterministic
我们说确定性的加密不可能是CPA安全的，
通过描述一个可以赢得CPA游戏的攻击者
encryption cannot be CPA secure by
describing an adversary that wins the CPA
这个选择明文攻击(CPA)的游戏。我简单地提醒大家
game. The chosen plain text attack game,
and let me quickly remind you how that
这个游戏的工作流程。这个游戏开始时，
攻击者选择发送两条明文信息M0和M0
works. The game starts by the adversary
sending two messages, M zero and M zero.
记得在这个游戏里，攻击者总是能得到
And remember that, in this game, the
adversary is always going to be given the
左边或右边的明文信息的加密结果
encryption of the left message or the
encryption of the right message. In this
这种情况下，由于左右两边的明文信息是一样的
case, since he used the same message in
both cases, both on the left and on the
攻击者将会得到信息M0的加密
right, he's simply gonna get the
encryption of the message M zero. In the
下一步中，攻击者会发送明文信息M0,M1。现在，他将获得
next step, he's gonna send the messages M
zero, M1. And now he's either gonna get
M0或M1的加密。攻击者的目标是
the encryption of M zero, or the
encryption of M1. And his goal is to tell
确定他得到的是哪一个信息的加密。但是由于
这个加密是确定的，攻击者很容易分辨
which one he got. But because the
encryption is deterministic, this is very
他只需要测试C是否等于C0
easy for him to do. All he has to do is
just test whether C is equal to C zero.
如果C等于C0，那么他就知道他获得的是M0的加密
And if C is equal to C zero, then he knows
that he got the encryption of M zero. If C
如果C不等于C0，那么他就知道他获得的是M1的加密
is not equal to C zero, he knows that he
got the encryption of M1. So he can output
所以如果C等于C0，攻击者输出0。
如果C不等于C0，攻击者就输出1
zero, if C is equal to C0 and output one,
if C is not equal to C0 and his advantage
攻击者在这个游戏中的优势是1。
这个优势已经是最大了
in this in this particular game would be
one. So it, it would be a high, as high an
意味着这个攻击者完全破坏了选择明文安全
advantage as possible which means that the
attacker completely defeats chosen
这是以形式化方法来表述，关于明文信息
plain text security. Okay so, this is just
a formal way of saying that the attacker
攻击者能学到比他应该知道的更多的信息
basically learns more information about
the plain text than he should. So, the
那么问题是，我们怎么办呢？实际上答案是
question is, what do we do? And it turns
out the solution is basically to restrict
限制能够使用单个密钥加密的信息的类型
the type of messages that can be encrypted
under a single key. And so, the idea is to
想法是，让加密者永远不要用单个密钥
来加密同样的明文信息
say that suppose the encryptor never ever,
ever encrypts the same message under a
换句话说，信息密钥对总是不同的
single key. In other words the message key
pair is always different and never
是永不重复的。那么对每个加密，要不改变明文
repeats. So that for every single
encryption, either the message changes, or
要不改变密钥，或者两个都改，但不能用同样的密钥
the key changes, but, or both change. But
it can't be that we encrypt the same
加密同样的明文两次。那么为什么会这样？
message twice under the same key. So why
would this ever happen? Well it turns out
实际上这里有很自然的情形。比如说
there are very natural cases where this
happens. For example, if the messages
如果明文正好是随机地，加密者加密密钥
happen to be random. Say you, the
encryptors encrypting keys and those keys,
这些密钥比如说有128个，会有很高的概率
you know, say are 128 the keys so,
they'll never actually with very high
这些密钥是不重复的。这里当我们加密密钥时
probability, they'll never repeat. In this
case when we're encrypting keys, in fact,
事实上，很有可能所有使用一个主密钥加密的
is very likely that all the messages that
are encrypted under one master key are
(这个主密钥出现在基于ID的加密(IBE)中)
明文是互不相同的，因为这些密钥不太可能重复
always distinct because, again, these keys
are very unlikely to ever repeat. The
另一个原因是，明文之所以不会重复，
是因为明文空间中的某些结构
other reason why messages would never
repeat is simply because of some structure
例如，如果我们是在加密唯一的用户ID
in the message space. For example, if all
we're encrypting are unique user IDs. So
那么试想一下，在数据库的例子中，
索引对应唯一的用户ID
imagine, in the database example, the
index corresponds to a unique user ID. And
如果每个用户在数据库中只有一条记录
if there's exactly one record in the
database for each user, that says that
也就是说，每个加密的记录包含一个加密的索引
every encrypted record basically contains
an encrypted index, where the index is
数据库中所有记录的索引都不一样。
所以信息不重复有这么两个原因
distinct for all records in the database.
Okay so these are two reasons why messages
这是很合理的，实际上也经常发生
might never repeat. And this is a fairly
reasonable thing that actually does happen
现在如果信息永不重复，我们也许可以
quite often in practice. So now if the
messages never repeat, now maybe we can
定义安全性，并构建机制以满足我们的定义
actually define security and actually give
constructions to satisfy our definitions.
那么这就是确定性选择明文攻击的概念的由来
So this motivates the concept of deterministic chosen plain text attacks and
我来解释一下它们的意思。通常我们把密码
let me explain what they mean. So as usual
we have a cipher defined as an encryption
定义为一对加密、解密算法。所以我们有一个
密钥空间，一个信息空间和一个密文空间
and a decryption algorithm. So we have a
key space, a message space and a cipher
我们要定义安全性，依照惯例使用两个实验来定义
text space and we're gonna define security
just as normal using two experiments.
实验0和实验1。这个游戏和之前的很类似
Experiment zero and experiment one. And
the game actually looks very similar, it's
与标准的选择明文攻击游戏几乎一样
almost an identical game to the standard
chosen plaintext attack game where
攻击者发送询问，那么你可以看到这些询问中
basically the attacker issues queries, so
you can see these queries consist of pairs
包含了明文信息M0和M1。通常它们的长度必须一样
of messages, M0 and M1. They, as usual
they have to be the same length and for
对于每个询问，攻击者要不获得M0的加密结果，
要不获得M1的加密结果
each query the attacker either gets the
encryption of M0 or the encryption of M1
攻击者可以反复这样操作。他可以这样做q次
and the attacker can do this again and
again. He can do this Q times, and at the
在游戏的最后，攻击者要判断他获得的
end of the game he's supposed to say
whether he got the encryptions of the left
是左边信息的加密，还是右边信息的加密
messages or the encryptions of the right
messages. So this is the standard chosen
这是标准的选择明文攻击游戏，但现在有一个警告
plain text attack game, but now there's
one extra caveat. Which is to say that, if
如果这一位b等于0，换句话说
the bit is equal to zero, if B is equal to
zero. In other words, the attacker always
攻击者总能看到左边明文的加密，那么碰巧
sees the encryption of the left messages,
then it so happens that the left messages
左边的信息都是不同的，换句话说，他不会两次看到
must all be distinct. In other words, he
will never get to see the encryption of
同一个信息的加密，因为这些左边的信息总是不同的
the same message twice, because these left
messages are always distinct. So if the
如果位b等于0，那么他不会看到同样的信息被同样的密钥加密
bit B is equal to zero, again, he'll never
see the same message encrypted under the
也是因为这些信息M0，M10到Mq0
same key. Because, again, these zero
messages, M1 zero to MQ zero, are all
都是不相同的。类似地，我们要求所有的
信息M1也都是不相同的
distinct. Similarly, we require that all
the one messages are also distinct. And so
如果b正好等于1，攻击者永远不会
that, again, if B happens to be equal to
one, the attacker will never see two
看到两条信息被同一个密钥加密。这一要求是说
messages encrypted under the same key.
Okay? So this requirement that the, all
所有这些信息互不相同，类似地，所有这些q个信息
these messages are distinct, and
similarly, all these Q messages are
互不相同。这里使用的原则是，加密者不会使用
distinct. Basically captures this use case
that the encryptor will never encrypt the
同一密钥多次加密同样的明文信息。因此
same message multiple times using one
particular key. And as a result, the
攻击者不能多次询问，用同样的密钥
对同样的信息进行加密的结果
attacker simply can't ask for, the
encryption of the same message multiple
现在，我应该指出，回到最初的攻击
times using the same key. Now, I should
point out as you go back to our, to the
我们回到确定性加密的CPA攻击
original attack, here. So, here we go back
to our CPA attack on deterministic
大家注意，事实上这不是一个确定性的CPA游戏
encryption, you notice that here, in fact,
this is not a deterministic CPA game,
因为这里攻击者确实两次问了同样的信息m0的加密
because, here, the attacker did ask for
the same message m0 to be encrypted twice.
事实上，在确定性的CPA游戏中，这个攻击是非法的
So, in fact, this attack would be an
illegal attack under the deterministic CPA
通过删除这种攻击，我们实际上可以
game. And by ruling out this attack we
actually make it plausible that we might
给出确定性CPA安全的机制
be able to give constructions that are
deterministic CPA secure. And so as usual
通常，我们说如果攻击者不能区分实验0和实验1
we say if the adversary cannot distinguish
experiment zero, when he's given the
在实验0中它得到左边信息的加密
encryption of the left messages, from
experiment one, when he's given the
在实验1中它得到右边信息的加密，那么这个机制是语义安全的
encryption of the right messages, then the
scheme is semantically secure. Under a
在一个确定性CPA攻击下，通常我们问
deterministic CPA attack. Okay. So as
usual, we ask for what's the probability
攻击者在实验0中输出1的概率是多少？
that the adversary outputs one in
experiment zero? What's the probability
攻击者在实验1中输出1的概率是多少？
如果这两个概率很接近
that the outputs one in experiment one?
Then if these probabilities are close then
那么他攻击这个机制的优势是可忽略的
his advantage in attacking the scheme is
negligible. And if that's true for all
如果这对所有有效攻击者都成立，那么我们说
这个机制在确定性的CPA攻击下是语义安全的
efficient adversaries then we say that the
scheme is semantically secure under
首先我想给大家看
deterministic CPA attack. So the first
thing I want to do is show you the cipher
带固定IV的CBC事实上不是确定的CPA安全的
block chaining with a fixed IV, in fact,
not deterministic CPA secure. And this a
这在实际中是一个常见的错误。有很多产品
common mistake that's used in practice.
There are many products that should be
应该使用确定性CPA安全的密码
using a cipher that's deterministic CPA
secure, but instead, they just use CBC
但它们却使用带固定IV的CBC，并假设这是个安全的机制
with a fixed IV and assume that's a secure
mechanism. And in fact, it's not and I
事实上，它并不是，我想给大家展示为什么。
假设我们有一个PRP正好定义在N位分组上
want to show you why. So suppose we have a
PRP that happens to operate on N bits
我们要以CBC模式使用这个PRP
blocks. And we're going to use this PRP in
CBC mode. So, you know, if there are five
如果信息中有5个分组，那么这个PRP E会被调用5次
blocks in the message then this PRP E will
be called five times to encrypt each one
来解密各个分组。攻击如下进行
of those blocks. Okay. So here's how the
attack's going to work. Well, the first
攻击者首先询问信息0^N1^N的加密结果
thing the adversary is going to do is he's
going to ask for the encryption of the
换句话说，第一个分组全是0
message as 0N, 1N. In other words, the
first block is all zeros and the second
第二个分组全是1。那么左边的信息等于右边的信息
block is all ones. So the left message is
equal to the right message here which
意味着他想得到信息0^N1^N的加密结果
means that he just wants the encryption of
this 0N, one to the N message. So let's
我们看到密文长什么样。为求完整性，我写下IV
see what the cipher text looks like. Well,
for completeness I'm gonna write the IV,
固定的IV，作为密文的第一个元素
the fixed IV, as the first element in the
ciphertext. And if you think about how
如果你考虑CBC然后工作，密文的第二个元素
CBC works and the second element in
the ciphertext is gonna be basically the
是IV异或明文第一个分组。在这个情况下
encryption of the IV XOR the first
block of the message. Well in our case the
第一个明文分组全是0，所以我们所加密的
first block of the message is all zeros so
really all we're encrypting is just a
就是一个固定的IV，那么密文的第二个分组
fixed IV. So the second block of the
ciphertext is simply gonna be the
将是这个固定IV的加密。接下来
encryption of this fixed IV. So next, what
the adversary's gonna do is, now he's
攻击者会输出两个单分组的信息
gonna output two messages that are a
single block. So the first message is
第一个信息在左边，是全0的分组
gonna be, the message on the left is gonna
be the all zeroes block. And the message
而右边的信息是全1的分组。观察到这是一个有效的询问
on the right is gonna be all ones block.
So observe that this is a valid query,
因为左边的信息不相同，右边的信息也不相同
because messages on the left are all
distinct. And the messages on the right
所以这些都是有效的确定性CPA询问
are also all distinct. So these are all
valid deterministic CPA queries. Now, what
现在，攻击者获得了什么样的回复？他会得到如下回复
does the attacker get in response? Well,
what he'll get in response is the
如果他获得了左边信息的加密
following. If he gets the encryption of
the message on the left. Then, well,
那么全是0的一个分组的明文信息被加密成什么了？
what's the encryption of the one block
message, zero to the N? It's simply the
就是固定IV的加密结果，就像我们之前看到的
encryption of the fixed IV, just as we saw
before. However, if he's getting the
不过，如果他获得右边信息的加密，那将是
encryption of the message on the right,
well, that's gonna be the encryption of 1 XOR
1异或固定IV后的加密。这是CBC加密的定义
the fixed IV. That's the definition
of, CBC encryption. So know, you can see
大家可以看到攻击将如何进行了。注意
basically how the attack is going to
proceed. You notice, if I, here I'll use a
我这里使用了不同的颜色。大家注意，
如果这两个分组正好是一样的
different color here. You notice if these
two blocks happen to be the same, then we
那么我们知道他收到了左边明文信息的加密，换句话说
know that he received the encryption of
the message on the left, in other words B
b等于0。如果它们不一样，攻击者就知道了b=1
is equal to zero. If they're not the same
then he knows that B is equal to one. Okay,
那么他就会输出0，如果这个密文分组C1
so he's gonna output zero if, you know, C
of one, which is this block, is equal to
等于这个分组C1的话，攻击者就会输出1
C1 of one, which is this block, and he's
gonna output one otherwise. So this
这就证实了带固定IV的CBC是根本不安全的
basically shows that CBC with a fixed IV
is completely insecure. Basically the
第一个分组可以分轻松破解。事实上，如果信息很短
first block can be very easily attacked.
And, in fact, if the messages are short
你可以构建字典，来完全破解类似于
you can again build dictionaries and
completely break systems that kind
带固定IV的CBC的系统，还希望它是确定的CPA安全的
of view CBC with a fixed IV hoping that
it's gonna be a deterministic CPA secure.
不要这么做。下节我们将看到安全的确定性的CPA机制
So don't do that. We're actually gonna see
secure deterministic CPA constructions in
那么我们还要再说一遍，如果你需要加密数据库的索引
the next segment. So I'll say one more
time, if you need to encrypt the database
以一致性的方式，不要使用带固定IV的CBC
index in a consistent manner, don't use
CBC with a fixed IV to do it. Use the
用我下节给大家展示的机制
schemes that I'm gonna show you in the
next segment. And so let me ask you the
那么关于固定IV的计数器模式，我问大家同样的问题
same question about counter mode with a
fixed IV. Is this gonna be a deterministic
这个是不是确定性的CPA安全呢？我提示一下大家
什么是带固定IV的计数器模式
CPA secure system or not? And here, I'm
reminding you what counter mode with a
我们联结固定IV，固定IV+1。。。一直到固定IV+L
fixed IV is. Basically, we concatenate the
fixed IV. Fixed IV plus one, Fixed IV plus
我们加密所有的这些计数器。我们联结这些加密结果
L. We encrypt all these counters. We
concatenate the results, we encrypt the
加密明文获得密文。大家是否认为这是确定性的CPA安全的？
message to get the cipher text. So if you
think this is gonna be deterministic CPA
我希望大家的答案是否定的，因为这是一个
secure. So I hope everybody said no,
because basically this is a onetime
一次性补齐的加密，如果我们使用这个一次性密码本
来加密不同的明文信息
padding encryption, and if we use this one
time pad to encrypt distinct messages,
我们会得到一个二次密码本。更精确地
basically we'll be getting a two time pad.
And to see more precisely, here I wrote
这里我写下了确定性CPA游戏。大家注意
down the, deterministic CPA game. So,
you notice what the attacker will do is he
攻击者开始时会询问信息m的加密结果
would start off by asking for the
encryption of the message m. So he would
他会得到信息m与固定IV的加密结果的异或
get here the message m XOR the encryption
of the fixed IV and then he's gonna ask
他会询问两个不同的信息m0和m1，它们都与m不同
for some two distinct messages m0 and m1
that's different from m. So, m, m0 and m1
所以m，m0和m1是三个不同的信息
are a three are all three are distinct
messages. And then what he'll get is the
然后攻击者会得到mb的加密，现在他可以实施标准的
encryption of mb and now he can simply
mount the standard, kinda two time pad
两次密码本攻击。如果这个等式成立，c异或c'等于m异或m0
attack. And if this equality here of c XOR c prime is equal to m XOR m zero, he
那么攻击者就知道了c'是m0的加密，否则
knows that c prime is the encryption of m
zero. And otherwise he knows it's the
他知道c'是m1的加密。那么他会以优势1完胜这场游戏
encryption of M1. So, again, he will
completely win this game with advantage
带固定IV的确定性的CPA
equals to one. Okay, so again deterministic CPA
with a fixed IV is also
也是方根不安全的，作为确定的CPA密码来说
completely insecure as a deterministic CPA
cipher. So, don't use any of those
不要使用这些机制，而是用我下节讲的机制
schemes, instead let's use the schemes I'm
going to describe in the next segment.